Guide to the University of Chicago Central Administration Letterbooks 1927-1957
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Central Administration. Letterbooks
1927-1957
39.5 linear feet (119 volumes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The University of Chicago Central Administration Letterbooks contain carbon copies of outgoing correspondence of university presidents, vice-presidents, and other officials, between the years 1927 and 1957. This correspondence covers academic and administrative matters.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Historical Note
The University of Chicago Central Administration Letterbooks cover the administrations of Max Mason (1925-1928), Robert Maynard Hutchins (1929-1951), and Lawrence A. Kimpton (1951-1960). Mason was the first President to come from outside the University. He oversaw a period of expansion, including the creation of a hundred new faculty positions, the completion of the hospitals, and a new football stadium. Under his successor, however, varsity football was eliminated; Hutchins sought to focus on cementing the University’s reputation for intellectual rigour, particularly at the undergraduate level, where he championed a liberal, non-specialized education. Despite his involvement with government projects on campus during wartime, notably the Manhattan Project, Hutchins was a defender of academic freedom who protected his faculty against post-war charges of communism. Kimpton’s administration was similarly ambitious, presiding over a controversial urban renewal project in Hyde Park to boost declining enrollment.
Scope Note
The University of Chicago Central Administration Letterbooks contain carbon copies of outgoing correspondence of university presidents, vice-presidents, and other officials, between the years 1927 and 1957. Each volume includes an index. The correspondence covers academic and administrative matters.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Mason Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Hutchins Administration. Records
University of Chicago. Office of the President. Kimpton Administration. Records
Subject Headings
Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-; Kimpton, Lawrence Alpheus, 1910-; Mason, Max, 1877-1961; University of Chicago. Administration; University of Chicago. Presidents
INVENTORY
- May 1-July 31, 1927 (Volume 1)
- August 1-October 31, 1927 (Volume 2)
- November 1-January 31, 1927-1928 (Volume 3)
- February 1-April 30, 1928 (Volume 4)
- May 1-July 31, 1928 (Volume 5)
- August 1-October 31, 1928 (Volume 6)
- November 1-January 31, 1928-1929 (Volume 7)
- February 1-April 30, 1929 (Volume 8)
- May 1-July 31, 1929 (Volume 9)
- August 1-October 31, 1929 (Volume 10)
- November 1-January 31, 1929-1930 (Volume 11)
- February 1-December 31, 1930 (Volume 12)
- January 1-April 30, 1931 (Volume 13)
- May 1-August 31, 1931 (Volume 14)
- September 1-December 31, 1931 (Volume 15)
- January 1-March 31, 1932 (Volume 16)
- April 1-June 30, 1932 (Volume 17)
- July 1-September 30, 1932 (Volume 18)
- October 1-December 31, 1932 (Volume 19)
- January 1-March 31, 1933 (Volume 20)
- April 1-July 8, 1933 (Volume 21)
- July 1-September 30, 1933 (Volume 22)
- October 1-January 31, 1933-1934 (Volume 23)
- January 1-March 31, 1934 (Volume 24)
- April 1-June 30, 1934 (Volume 25)
- July 1-September 30, 1934 (Volume 26)
- October 1-December 31, 1934 (Volume 27)
- January 1-March 31, 1935 (Volume 28)
- April 1-June 30, 1935 (Volume 29)
- July 1-September 30, 1935 (Volume 30)
- October 1-December 31, 1935 (Volume 31)
- January 1-March 31, 1936 (Volume 32)
- April 1-June 30, 1936 (Volume 33)
- July 1-September 30, 1936 (Volume 34)
- October 1-December 31, 1936 (Volume 35)
- January 1-March 31, 1937 (Volume 36)
- April 1-June 30, 1937 (Volume 37)
- July 1-September 30, 1937 (Volume 38)
- October 1-December 31, 1937 (Volume 39)
- January 1-March 31, 1938 (Volume 40)
- April 1-June 30, 1938 (Volume 41)
- July 1-September 30, 1938 (Volume 42)
- October 1-December 31, 1938 (Volume 43)
- January 1-March 31, 1939 (Volume 44)
- April 1-June 30, 1939 (Volume 45)
- July 1-September 30, 1939 (Volume 46)
- October 1-December 31, 1939 (Volume 47)
- January 1-March 31, 1940 (Volume 48)
- April 1-June 30, 1940 (Volume 49)
- July 1-September 30, 1940 (Volume 50)
- October 1-December 31, 1940 (Volume 51)
- January 1-March 31, 1941 (Volume 52)
- April 1-June 30, 1941 (Volume 53)
- July 1-September 30, 1941 (Volume 54)
- October 1-December 31, 1941 (Volume 55)
- January 1-March 31, 1942 (Volume 56)
- April 1-June 30, 1942 (Volume 57)
- July 1-September 30, 1942 (Volume 58)
- October 1-December 31, 1942 (Volume 59)
- January 1-March 31, 1943 (Volume 60)
- April 1-June 30, 1943 (Volume 61)
- July 1-September 30, 1943 (Volume 62)
- October 1-December 31, 1943 (Volume 63)
- January 1-March 31, 1944 (Volume 64)
- April 1-June 30, 1944 (Volume 65)
- July 1-September 30, 1944 (Volume 66)
- October 1-December 31, 1944 (Volume 67)
- January 1-March 31, 1945 (Volume 68)
- April 1-June 30, 1945 (Volume 69)
- July 1-September 30, 1945 (Volume 70)
- October 1-December 31, 1945 (Volume 71)
- January 1-March 31, 1946 (Volume 72)
- April 1-June 30, 1946 (Volume 73)
- July 1-September 30, 1946 (Volume 74)
- October 1-December 31, 1946 (Volume 75)
- January 1-March 31, 1947 (Volume 76)
- April 1-June 30, 1947 (Volume 77)
- July 1-September 30, 1947 (Volume 78)
- October 1-December 31, 1947 (Volume 79)
- January 1-March 31, 1948 (Volume 80)
- April 1-June 30, 1948 (Volume 81)
- July 1-September 30, 1948 (Volume 82)
- October 1-December 31, 1948 (Volume 83)
- January 1-March 31, 1949 (Volume 84)
- April 1-June 30, 1949 (Volume 85)
- July 1-September 30, 1949 (Volume 86)
- October 1-December 31, 1949 (Volume 87)
- January 1-March 31, 1950 (Volume 88)
- April 1-June 30, 1950 (Volume 89)
- July 1-September 30, 1950 (Volume 90)
- October 1-December 31, 1950 (Volume 91)
- January 1-March 31, 1951 (Volume 92)
- April 1-June 30, 1951 (Volume 93)
- July 1-September 30, 1951 (Volume 94)
- October 1-December 31, 1951 (Volume 95)
- January 1-March 31, 1952 (Volume 96)
- April 1-June 30, 1952 (Volume 97)
- July 1-September 30, 1952 (Volume 98)
- October 1-December 31, 1952 (Volume 99)
- January 1-March 31, 1953 (Volume 100)
- April 1-June 30, 1953 (Volume 101)
- July 1-September 30, 1953 (Volume 102)
- October 1-December 31, 1953 (Volume 103)
- January 1-March 31, 1954 (Volume 104)
- April 1-June 30, 1954 (Volume 105)
- July 1-September 30, 1954 (Volume 106)
- October 1-December 31, 1954 (Volume 107)
- January 1-March 31, 1955 (Volume 108)
- April 1-June 30, 1955 (Volume 109)
- July 1-September 30, 1955 (Volume 110)
- October 1-December 31, 1955 (Volume 111)
- January 1-March 31, 1956 (Volume 112)
- April 1-June 30, 1956 (Volume 113)
- July 1-September 30, 1956 (Volume 114)
- October 1-December 31, 1956 (Volume 115)
- January 1-March 31, 1957 (Volume 116)
- April 1-June 30, 1957 (Volume 117)
- July 1-September 30, 1957 (Volume 118)
- October 1-December 31, 1957 (Volume 119)